<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<part xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
	xml:id="migrating-from-perl" 
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">
	<title>Migrating from the Perl UI</title>
	
	<partintro>
		<para>This section will list some points of interest when migrating from the Perl UI.</para>
	</partintro>
	
	<chapter xml:id="migrating-cgi-transforms">
		<title>CGI transforms</title>
		
		<para>
			CGI transforms have been re-implemented but sometimes the behaviour on some limit cases (Such as parameters with no values on the
			left end or right end of the rule) was difficult to figure out from the Perl code.
		</para>
		
		<para>You'll probably need to check that your existing CGI Transforms works as expected with the new Public UI</para>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter xml:id="faceted-nav-transforms">
		<title>Faceted navigation transforms</title>
		
		<para>
			Faceted navigation transforms have been re-implemented in Groovy (Previously in Perl). Any existing
			<literal>faceted_navigation_transform.cfg</literal> will need to be ported to Groovy into <literal>faceted_navigation_transform.groovy</literal>.
		</para>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter xml:id="query-transforms">
		<title>Query transforms</title>
		
		<para>
			Query transforms have been re-implemented in Groovy (Previously in Perl) and merged with the "custom hook scripts" feature.
			Any existing <literal>query_transform.cfg</literal> will need to be ported to Groovy, and placed in a relevant hook script.
		</para>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter xml:id="classic-xml">
		<title>Using classic XML format</title>
		
		<para>
			The Java Public UI is able to generate classic <literal>xml.cgi</literal> format using an XSL transformation. Just use <literal>search.classic</literal>
			as URL controller to trigger the transformation.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Most of the format is correctly emulated but some tags are missing because it was either too complicated to match the new structure with the old one,
			or because the feature was mostly unused. This is the case for:
			<simplelist>
				<member>Faceted navigation</member>
				<member>Tier bars</member>
			</simplelist>
		</para>
	</chapter>	

</part>