<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
	xml:id="criteria" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">

	<title>Criteria for choosing</title>
	
	<para>Here are the relevant criteria to consider when choosing our template engine.</para>
	
	<simplesect>
		<title>Simplicity &amp; usability</title>
		
		<para>
			We want to keep it simple as NickScript is currently. The language should be easy to understand and fast to learn (at least
			for the basics). It shouldn't require specific skills other than web design / basic web developments. 
		</para>
		<para>
			Form development should be the easiest possible, with clear error messages in case of errors.
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	
	<simplesect>
		<title>Flexibility</title>
		
		<para>
			The system should be flexible enough to cover unexpected use case. It should be able to provide an <code>EvalPerl</code> like feature
			in a secure fashion.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The system should be easily extensible with a plug-in mechanism.
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	
	<simplesect>
		<title>Performance</title>
		
		<para>
			Rendering a template should be quick, including on the client-side if we choose a Javascript based template engine. How quick ?
			let's say we want to keep it around 10ms for a start for the default form file.
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	
	<simplesect>
		<title>Support &amp; community</title>
		
		<para>
			Relying on a third party template system saves us having to write and maintain our own. We have to make sure that the one we choose is
			backed up by a solid community. Relases should be made regularly to fix bugs / add new features, and we have to be able to get community support.
		</para>
	</simplesect>

</chapter>
