<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en"
	xml:id="criteria" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">

	<title>Criteria for choosing</title>
	
	<para>Here are the relevant criteria I identified to consider when choosing our template engine.</para>
	
	<simplesect>
		<title>Simplicity &amp; usability</title>
		
		<para>
			We want to keep it simple as NickScript is currently. The language should be easy to understand and fast to learn (at least
			for the basics). It shouldn't require specific skills other than web design / basic web development. 
		</para>
		<para>
			Form development should be the easiest possible, with clear error messages in case of errors in the form file.
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	
	<simplesect>
		<title>Flexibility</title>
		
		<para>
			The system should be flexible enough to cover unexpected use cases. It should be able to provide an <code>EvalPerl</code> like feature
			in a secure way.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The system should be easy to extend, with a plug-in mechanism or possibility to add directives.
			This is an strong requirement if we want to match current NickScript features: We should be able to provide a base library of tags or
			plug-ins, for example to provide the equivalent of <code>&lt;s:PrevNext /&gt;</code>.
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	
	<simplesect>
		<title>Performance</title>
		
		<para>
			Rendering a template should be quick, including on the client-side if we choose a Javascript based template engine. But how quick do we want
			it to be ? Could we consider 10ms to render a page reasonable ?
		</para>
		
		<remark>
			I didn't benchmark the performance during my experiments as proper benchmarking takes time and I focused on usability and flexibility to narrow
            down the list of potential candidates. For what I could observe every engine I tested seemed to be reasonably fast. However we'll have to properly benchmark
            the template engine we choose to confirm that impression.
		</remark>
	</simplesect>
	
	<simplesect>
		<title>Support &amp; community</title>
		
		<para>
			Relying on a third party template system saves us having to write and maintain our own. We have to make sure that the one we choose is
			backed up by a solid community. Releases should be made regularly to fix bugs / add new features, and we have to be able to get community support.
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	
	<simplesect>
		<title>Existing form files migration</title>
		
		<para>
			We should be able to migrate easily existing form files to a new syntax. While it's reasonable to assume that we won't be able to provide a 100% accurate
			conversion of existing form files, we should provide a tool that converts most of an existing form file.
		</para>
	</simplesect>

</chapter>
